okay I believe it is recording
so welcome everyone we're in our first
meeting for cohort 8 in Chapter
2 so we'll head over to the chapter 2
page and to chapter 2 in the
book and let's just begin does anyone
have any
thoughts quotes sections that they'd
like to pick up
with about chapter
2 like what was something that stayed
with them about chapter
2 whether just a phrase
or what is the low road what did you
expect the low road to be what did you
walk away feeling that the low road
[Music]
was I I like the question I just had so
did you tell me when that's most
relevant place to put that question in
the audience
maybe ask again just to be clear so I
feel there are two levels of looking at
the text uh when we talk about the
action perception cycle and uh it says
that we have preferences but it can be
interpreted I think in two ways the body
having preferences or me as the
experiencing subject having those
preferences and so it feels like it
alternates between those Cycles as if
it's the same thing at least it does not
distinguish quite clearly between those
two levels of looking at it uh and I was
thinking is this distinction even
analytically Justified and second if so
how then should one this alternate
between those two
lenses obviously there's a lot of ways
to go into that just to respond narrowly
and analytically active inference does
not require a nested or a multi-level
model the first part of the book is
going to build up towards just looking
at single layer models so not going into
higher
order human type cognition
differentiating between minds and bodies
and aware and subconscious and multiple
types of experiences and all of this it
doesn't have to be an embodied system we
could just be talking about a a
dynamical oscillating system or even
simpler systems where bringing out this
framework would be total Overkill so no
specific type of articulation between
any kind of body and mind is presupposed
by the framework at all which is why it
almost always comes back to active
inference saying less so you can say
more so the inquiry starts to look like
you posit a kind of structure for a
given body and mind and experiencer and
then what kinds of experiments or
measurements reduce your uncertainty
about that space of hypothesis but it's
not to be found in the
framework I I do acknowledge the the
general class of subject matter of
active influence uh but they do also
claim that we as humans fall under the
subject matter we are a cell systems and
therefore we are also uh subjected to
this notion of having these pre
preferences like also statical dynamical
systems could have those preferences um
but then you know preferences seem to
have a double layer we experience
ourselves as having preferences and most
of the times we are like conscious of it
and those preferences ascribed To Us by
the active inflence Paradigm and then
how do these two Notions relate to each
other so so it sounds like you're you're
trying to distinguish between two sets
of preferences is that
right uh the preferences uh we should
have uh by the active inference
framework which sees as systems and we
have preferences like those are like the
Tendencies we we see my systems to to
evolve towards and to also avoid entropy
those kind of preferences ascribed by
the active influence framework but also
the active preferences we as normal
humans seem to experience that we have a
certain will and certain desire and a
wish to go to certain States for and and
those things seem to contradict at first
glance for me you know with depression
or like the Suicidal Tendencies etc etc
so how do you feel about this so uh the
appeal to me so far has been that I
think those personal preferences are
also dictated by these sort of like
entropic forces that um steer us
towards I don't know
um towards like a a set of preferences
that is
uh I don't know how explain it yet but
just to throw it in because I also
thought about certain kind of religious
as such but someone can for example
smoke having full Consciousness about
the harmful effects about his losing his
life span destroying his lungs and yet
do the act of smoking so how does do two
things relate then you
think so this is I think this is like
the um the one of the most interesting
Parts about this I think so in in some
way somewhere along the line that person
has been I guess building a set of
preferences that um um makes them
probably more comfortable to you know
choose smoking or something there
there's some reason that this person has
to be choosing these things because
maybe it makes them feel a certain way
about themselves or about how they fit
in the world or something um you know
it's probably so okay I think I think I
understand what the general theme is
about active inference explanations and
is that if this seems to be
discrepancies between those two level
preferences at the system base and
experimental base then explanations to
be s in the complexity of the model
which seemingly can for
example can contradict the lower the
lowest simplistic systems of the model
so that the answer is always then to be
s in the complexity of the system is
that you think
the right how
else I think Malcolm's trying to talk
but I can't really hear
him go ahead
Malcolm okay volume thing I mean sure
short answer yes nested models or
interacting models of this is true of a
linear aggression model this is just
general to any kind of explanation of
variance if something is not being
explained by a model structure within a
level often it's it's um accounted for
elsewhere but like before jumping to the
psychological
connections of the terms like preference
and trying to associate it like you gave
an example of a behavior so even just
speaking really broadly with a single
layer Behavior so it could be that the
Habit the E the prior on action is such
that a given action is selected like
turning a certain direction or you could
localize the repetitive behavior
causality in the be so the person has
they don't understand the consequences
of a given action like their skin itches
and they don't know that not that doing
this will do that or it could be Inc in
preference it's like so the structure of
the inquiry is to develop these kinds of
precision Psychiatry or cognitive models
to differentiate hypothesis so thinking
about it qualitatively speculatively
mixing ontologies combining experiential
and Technical elements those are early
and sort of generative phases and then
yes you start to specify generative
models following like the chapter six
type recipe or using other approaches
and then you start to look at the
relative merits of these different
approaches let let's return to yeah yeah
okay M go for
it oh you're muted but then
continue yeah I don't want to straight
the topic too much on one end and if
someone else supposed to to speak as
well yeah let's please return to chapter
two and if somebody has a specific quote
or or question or idea about chapter
2 I just wanted to to add one more idea
I I had up your um question mon like the
idea of contradicting preferences and
how system would like as you said maybe
you want to smoke like you have this
preference of wanting to smoke and
wanting to smoke and how this affects
your um selection of a policy of an
action and actually I was just reading
yesterday a nice paper of like the
attachment style of where this
experiment where the children are
playing then the mother gets out
and they are crying then she gets back
in and depending on the attachment style
the the curely attached child would will
be angry but still get to the mom and
knows what to do while the um
disorganized child will like be in a
unsettled mood when the mother gets in
and it's not really like a clear policy
so there's a high uncertainty like when
you um refer to the active
inference um selection policy selection
calculation a high uncertainty what
policy is actually the best policy I
just should I should choose in that
moment given the observations I have and
the contradicting
preferences
something great Ben's liing a little bit
Yeah the example you offered with the
smoking will maybe Behavior as we maybe
see quit smoking
but I don't
know thank you Ben yeah just a short
comment yeah I I do acknowledge like
there's a lot of explanatory power in
active influence
yes okay awesome so let's kind of return
to a chapter two anyone you know write
in the chat or or
yeah um so I okay I can start with
something in chapter two sure um so one
of the sort of questions I was trying to
follow along in the chapter to see if
there was an answer for is um is uh
essentially like how how a decision is
actually made so they talk a lot about a
couple times about how there's like a
balance between these two terms in the
um variation of free energy right how
one of them is like you know is about
exploring the space and one of them is
about um exploiting the
space um but I wasn't really clear on
how a decision is actually made so they
talk about how like um the policy is
like the relative balance between these
two terms but at what point is a
decision made is it like is there a
threshold somewhere that um like an
agent actually uses to say okay actually
I need more information so I'm going to
explore the space more versus
like okay I actually I I want to obtain
this this preferred State more than I
care about getting information so I'm
going to um you
know uh you know seek out this state or
something it like I guess my question is
is there a threshold like how is a
decision actually made yeah Sylvia do
you want to add something to
that yes and I feel like maybe that
threshhold could be determined by um
that agents prior or preferences to
begin with for example even personality
some people tend to be more Rich
conservative While others are Risk
Takers and in a way that fresh would
differ from those people or we look at
people with psychiatric disorders they
have very rigid pray about the reality
that is clearly kind of Mal adductive
even but to them it makes sense to
choose certain policies or make
decisions at a certain point while
normal people might think that well
that's not rational or that doesn't even
make sense so I guess the fres home
might be very dependent on the contest
and also that agents like prior to begin
with for that specific like goal or
desirable outcome that they are pursuing
after okay so so there is a threshold
then that is the
idea um yes I I believe
so another another aspect of this just
operationally when you implement these
models is here's you know one one
tutorial one place to look at this is
you have a prior on policy so that's
before the observation comes in How
likely are you to do different things
50% to turn left 50% to turn right an
observation comes in the policy prior is
updated to the policy
posterior through the calculation of
expected free energy
so the prior on policy was even and then
the pragmatic value and the epistemic
value of these two Alternatives reweight
them so now it's 70% likely to turn
right 30% to turn left and then from
that posterior distribution one action
is
sampled and then that is
emitted so in this simulation
every time Step In Action is
decided now the question of when an
action is taken is done with a few
different approaches one approach is to
have a null action like have weight as
an
action another approach is to have a
nested model where at the highest level
of the model you have weight or
act and then within act you have just
the choices of action gotcha okay an
action is selected because there's an
unrolling continuous action so then it's
just are you trying to model something
that happens at every single time step
like gas or break but then if you want
to include neither you could either
include that in the base level or you
have this nested model with and then and
then that's where would you'd get into
variation in those cognitive parameters
what are someone's priors on How likely
they are to use the gas or the BR
what are the B Matrix reflecting
people's understanding of what happens
when you hit the gas or the break what
are their preferences about what they
expect to see and prefer to see from
sensory
observations achieved by hitting the gas
in the
break got it that's that makes sense so
it's like yeah it's it's a sampling of
policies not just a simple
threshold It's s actions over
policies one action gets sampled so
carried through time is a distribution
over action
choices and then that gets sampled one I
mean this is a great line and this is
like when it's like wait what is active
inference this is a an important thing
to walk away from chapter 2 with what is
the simple but fundamental Advance
offered by active
inference this is the question
so that's that's an interesting thing to
to ask and
learn and how does that fit into the low
road okay let's look at some of the
questions in chat quickly okay John
would you say preferences are revealed
by priors which are revealed by
observations I mean revealed to whom
when you're the one writing the
generative model you wrote all those
variables in your code in a given
situation where you're reducing your
uncertainty about those
parameters you could imagine a situation
where you're reducing uncertainty about
one of those variables based upon your
assessment of another one but sure there
could be a situation where through
observation which is kind of the
ultimate empirical
interface you are learning about
priors but priors are a bit broad
because priors in Bas in statistics
refer to basically anything before they
get updated but then they become the
posterior relative to them being prior
to that observation but the posterior is
again prior to the next observation so
it's usually a little bit more helpful
to specify like prior on
what um can I answer that uh also to
John so yeah I was thinking about this a
couple days ago this is really
interesting because what do you have
when some like say somebody experienced
something new for the first time maybe
they've I don't know they've never gone
like rock climbing or something and they
were seen it before and then they go and
all of a sudden it's really exciting and
they're they have all these different
experiences about rock climbing or
something and now they love it and they
didn't know that before so in that case
their their their priors were revealed
by observations right like there has to
be some mechanism in this where somebody
can like you know be adding onto their
their priors because there has to be new
you know room for new experiences
to be had so in to that question I think
I would say
yes yes Al great point also within the
textbook like within the early part of
working within a single layer model and
so on it's a structurally fixed model so
the thermometer is dealing in degrees
temperature and it can quantitatively
adjust within degrees temperature but
it's not going to start seeing or
modifying color that gets into the space
of structure learning
where you have
model structure as an inference Target
and that's where the Assembly of new
Concepts and changes in the structure of
affordances or or anything come into
play um okay Andreas what's the
difference between predictions and
preferences so as used here preferences
are a prior Distribution on
observation that
reflect expectations over observation
consistent with being a cost or a
constraint function also sometimes
called preferences and it's used in
pragmatic value calculation predictions
are anticipations about something
usually about
observations
okay anyone again can can write
something or or um raise their hand but
gu you could write that down somewhere
it's all recorded you can return to but
yeah and and also the these
definitions are the active inference
ontology the definitions of
terms and and just it's just
about understanding um where is it
referring to like continent scale like
prior again but it could be a prior on
anything so there's little that can
be can't go too much into saying what
about this prior because it's just like
a prior on what so a lot of it is just
knowing when do you need to to just add
more
detail and when it comes down to it it's
about the specific generative model
constructed um but thinking about the
structure of the book a little bit
remember we're in the first half so
we're in the background and theory and
learning area chapter 1 was
introductory chapter 2 and three are
going to bring us to active inference
from two different directions the low
road and the high road chapter 2 is
going to do this from the low road
chapter 3 is going to do this from The
High Road chapter 4 is going to be the
active inference generative model which
is kind of like this boundary
artifact which is the target of our
construction it's used in computational
inference
looked at from the low road it's
constructed According to some of these
topics looked at from the high road it's
consistent under the free energy
principle chapter four chapter five is a
review on a few different generative
models that have been constructed in
Maman human
Neuroscience so that's the first half of
the book
is Introduction and then two roads
converging on a certain type of artifact
that we
construct chapter 5 giving examples of
how that artifact is
used
so it's it's um it's it's going to be
like two different complimentary
approaches the low road is like a build
it from the ground
up computer science or
engineering starting with probabilistic
modeling
and Baye
equation working towards building
integrated
models that have both perceptual
inference and planning or action
selection as
inference that's like the build it from
the ground up it's like if you were
building a cognitive framework for an
agent embodied or cyber physical or
whatever it it was and you wanted to
combine the inbound signal processing
element
with the outbound action selection
control theoretic element and you wanted
to integrate the inbound and the
outbound into a unified model and then
apply it to things like brains using
tractable approximations like
variational
inference that's kind of what happens on
the low road is like building cognitive
models that unify perception cognitive
phenomena and action
in a ground up
way we'll get to chapter 3 in the high
road when we get there but that's sort
of the low road and and that's
um how from just primary
considerations in statistical modeling
of cognitive
systems one reaches something basically
like active
inference just from considering the
question of modeling agents
that's in figure
1.2 but then chapter 2 goes into this in
in more
depth and and starts with this again
kind of Step by Step bottom up but for
those who haven't seen much of basian
Statistics before this is kind of a
good
Motif like we have a prior belief about
objects in our
hand whether they're frog or apple not a
secret third thing again that would be
the structure learning um and then an
observation comes in and the beliefs
about the object are updated that's
perceptual
inference and something analogous occurs
with action inference where we have a
prior on what we we are apt to do then
the observation comes in and then we
have a posterior on what we're apt to do
which get sampled from and that was kind
of the question
earlier okay anyone want to ask
something or I can copy one of the
questions from the chat
and yeah okay
Henry yeah hi so I have a I have a
question about
equation equation 2.5 so the variational
free energy definition
yes um so I guess these are two two
quite simple but interrelated questions
the first is like um in the
complexity versus accuracy
factorization um oh sorry the Divergence
the Divergence in evidence
factorization the uh the Divergence is
like computed with respect to the
approxim posterior um when like
canonically the you'd compute this with
respect to the uh the true the true
distribution is this just because if it
was the other way around it wouldn't be
equivalent to like the energy entropy
formation and it's a like a post talk
justification or or is it per more like
perers than than
that um does that make sense can we talk
talk freely or sorry is it like uh
directed questioning or can I
just respond to this question if you
have a thought yeah yeah yeah um yeah so
my my understanding there was that it
was with respect to the variational
because we don't know the true
posterior right so that I mean that's
the whole point right like we use Q
because we don't know what p is so we
approximate it with
Q uh yeah I I was just wondering because
like that that final term like the um
the additional quantity over the the
true evidence like we can't we can't
compute that anyway because we we can't
compute the the true the true posterior
so we'd use one of the other two
factorizations to like plug in plug in
the numbers and and we show their
equivalent to the third is that is that
correct yeah two two um answers here
just practically one of them is when you
implement the equation these three
decompositions are equivalent but when
you look at the code like for pmdp or
something like that you will find it's
often only implemented using one of them
and there's probably situations where
implementing using one of these
decompositions or another have different
computational performance a second
answer that's really important is you
pointed out that the evidence term is
fixed and doesn't depend on Q so when
we're interested in variational gradient
descent the evidence term is actually a
way to kind of quarantine the overall
likelihood of the data
and only follow Delta F which is
ultimately what we're going to use
anyway that's why the overall actual F
will be like 83
1114 but that's that's like looking at
the least squares error for a linear
aggression model it doesn't matter what
the real number is it's about within a
model like following the gradient on it
so this is a really good way just to say
well whatever the evidence is whatever
the likelihood is of the data we're
going to minimize the
Divergence by doing so and following
that Tailwind minimize the variational
free
energy whether that convex optimization
happens to be up here or down
here um
Sylvia um yeah I have a more General
question but just adding to this I was
thinking when we talk about um free
energy or variation of free energy and
saying that it has an upper bound is it
correct to actually perceive it or
simplify it as like you know to see that
it could be an
overestimate of the actual surprise the
surprise that we can't really you know
no the the true uncertainty that is out
there but we are giving it an estimate
to make sure that we can reduce it
regardless you know by our model like is
that a correct way of perceiving it yeah
absolutely so when the process
generating observations is the same
model family as the variational
distribution so gaussian process in the
world and we're going to use a gaussian
variational estimator
then the variational free energy will
conver converge to the actual generative
function whereas if the generative
function in the world were something
just weird or or
bodal you still within the variational
family of choice would be doing the best
you can by reducing the Divergence but
that could be hopelessly far
away so that's why the it's an upper
bound that's always equal to or greater
than because the best you could do would
be if the variational family were the
right family to exactly become
congruous with the data generating
function but in the situation where the
data generating function is anything
else then you'll be minimizing your
variational free energy to some point
that is
slightly um not exactly minimizing
surprise on the target distribution but
it's the best that could be done within
that constrained easily optimizable
interpretable
family yes that makes sense um the
general question that I had was um as we
were talking about advancement and what
are the key implications of active
influence treating perception and action
as part of the same cycle with this
shared objective rather than the
separate processes with like distinct
goals and how does this unified
framework this coherence apply to real
world I'm just really curious about how
everyone sees the potential of at
influence in relation to like advancing
their FS because like for me with
someone having a background in
Psychology I think it's a really nice
way of putting very fragmented theories
in different branches together and to
have like one unified um explanation so
I'm just curious about you know how
other people are taking it um from the
perspective of their
fields anyone can go for it but those
are awesome questions that's like
literally the whole
Fields but are we gonna have a special
theory for every brain region every
cognitive phenomena or what happens when
we do have unified approaches
yeah M than anyone else yes I was just
Al like wondering because I do not know
this the scope of active inference
explanatory power so also know it's
limits so I was actually interested are
there any like limits that what we can
speak of about till we can only use
inference for these matters but not for
these matters is there anything or do
you guys if you Dani fman I think you're
most red well red on active inference uh
think it's everything that they can
explain anything could be
modeled but whether to anyone any given
model of a given thing is satisfactory
is a totally outside
question so the explanatory scope of the
framework
generically is similar to like saying
well what's the explanatory scope of
Statistics you could model any
distribution but does it say anything
about the height of these children in
this classroom or why this happens here
no but could it be used to model why
that happens there for that thing yes is
that a tiny engineering project or is
that a mega engineering project that's
the
question is it something where we're
going to reach a satisfying account
easily uh um the purpose I I can I
forget who's the name of the
psychologist the lady psych anyway my
own purpose is trying to figure out how
to integrate or find coherence
across uh Dimensions that are operating
when you watch a movie or a video
basically the the text or the copy the
uh the cinematography and the music
they're all coming in through different
perceptual systems but they have to
create unified immersive experience and
the predictions we're trying to make uh
our audience responses I've actually
done some experiments with that because
we have ways of separating the
cinematography from the storytelling
from the the meaning being communicated
by the music and how that parallels the
meaning being communicated by the uh um
uh in terms of semantics and so on so
that you know you know that's that just
just is a way of saying how I think this
stuff will apply I'm trying to predict
audience responses to
creative and it turns out AI is really
good at coding the creative and making
guesses already about what's going on
and then when I show it actual audience
responses like oh I was wrong here I was
wrong there and so I'm trying to improve
the model over time and that's that's
actually why I'm in the
class awesome that's going to come up
like in chapter six this is there's some
latent underlying phenomena like a frog
or a well performed multimodal
performance well actually an interesting
thing we just ran across the other day I
don't know if you ever heard of tslot
subjective
correlative no it's it's a literary
theory that the you know the Nobel prize
winning poet TS earlier came up with
basically saying that if you want to
evoke a specific
emotion there is there is a unique
sequence of objects in your perceptual
world that if you go through that
sequence will evoke that very particular
emotion it says so that there's actually
an objective sequence of perceptions
that lines up with your associative
memory system basically I you wrote an
essay with it and stuff I'll try to
forward it to the group cool I mean this
is kind of a general madlib structure is
re-approaching X
from an active inference perspective
like what was pragmatism about or what
was this about or how could this be yeah
those are especially if those
connections haven't been made writing
those pieces out and footnoting it is an
awesome way to to open up your thinking
and footnote it and also well if you
take it one step further it's actually a
way of generating new
data that too you know so that you know
so the goal is obviously get to a
self-learning situ situation every time
you connect ideas because you're making
connections that the AI isn't it just
it's a Continuum it knows a lot of stuff
but if you connect the dots for them
you're like being a neuron in the thing
basically it can it it can create new do
data on on meaningful connections that
it wouldn't see without your
help I think that you know driving
towards a central role for human beings
in the interaction with Ai and and and
and and and the the theoretical
framework being something like active
inference
so okay um mon then
Al I was also very interested in
thinking about how uh to interpret what
active INF is doing if you're like a
modeler in mind so uh so there's like
some higher goal to be happy for example
and to be happy you have found a sub
goal method for that and that in itself
also becomes a goal and then you ask for
the same goal how to achieve this etc
etc then you guy kind of see this this
scheming down way and how how does this
thinking relate to active inference and
how they choose certain policies like a
sequence of actions which generates
observations in line with some prior
um is this this this notion of high will
low will to be see in the nested models
or
uh should we like relieve all these
Notions of old and only think of active
inference
[Music]
terms lot of ways to go with that like
keep that feeling and channel as open as
it can be and really look at the
textbook for what it says and then
whether those Lego pieces were exactly
what you sought or whether you see that
you need to build up a ton of pieces to
get to the sophistication and the
interplays that you're talking about
then you'll have the grammar to go about
that but you may find that it's
literally addressed within a single
layer and that you're talking about the
interplay of two kinds of variables
within a simple model at a single layer
or you may find that you're thinking
more about nested
models and then you'll have the grammar
to actually go about building
those
Adam uh yeah I I was so regarding
equations 2.5 and I think
2.6 Etc I was wondering if those are
derived anywhere mathematically and
because it seems like they're derived
sort of theistically is there anywhere
where I can see where they're
actually yeah yeah so um here in the
equation
rows um
um here and these are just tiny examples
of the absolutely transformative
contributions that people can make first
off with their written questions also
with derivations if they understand so
this is I believe from yakob
smackle here is equation
2.5 oh you know these are materials that
aren't in the textbook The Textbook is
just like the tip of the iceberg and we
can go a lot further and connect a lot
of the paths so here's 2.5 one of the
big pieces about
2.5 that that um like really helps
clarify it is the the route of
derivation is actually Row one goes to
two and Row one goes to three there may
also be a path to go from two to three
but that was very helpful to understand
that there's a path from 1 to two and 1
to three um there should be if they're
equivalent right yeah there better be
yeah yeah I'm sure there's a way to do
it but but just in terms of ones that
can fit on a single slides yeah and then
2.6
um Jonathan
shock has let's see if this link still
works there there may be another updated
or published version but Jonathan shock
who's a a math
professor
um yeah he's done some derivations on
expected free energy as well okay nice
yeah so those are good um yeah here's
his and this is in the math learning
group so like you know it's awesome that
people have all these questions like
that's literally what the questions are
for is is just add a question
and write it out everything that people
are typing and here adding the resources
that are relevant like please in the
time between enrich what we
have and and add
more and add your thoughts like imagine
that these questions are being asked by
people right now and the ones that
you're excited about adding information
to just go for it okay nice yeah there's
a ton of material on the on this we I
haven't really gotten to half of it yet
so
yeah this is also is kind of a fun piece
about applying active inference to
topics like this was just done with all
by all I generated synthetic domains and
then I just applied each domain to and
from active inference using
llm so this got ridiculously far oh in
starting to to apply active inference to
you know ATM transactions and blockchain
and chemistry and things like that
so understanding how to even use the
exence
tools to project to and from active
inference ontology and techniques is
already extremely
productive okay very cool thanks thanks
for
that yeah was someone else going to say
something I have I have one more quick
go for it um so on page
37 figure
2.6 I kind of wanted to understand that
diagram just a little bit I think I do
so um my understanding of this is saying
okay so like at the top level there's
the equation for the for the expect free
energy and then below it are different
decompositions you can make if you omit
certain terms so like would that cor or
does that correspond to like if you um
if you know you have a different I don't
know like decision regime in your
certain use case would you decide to
Omit a certain term because you're
trying
to um I don't know like structure the
learning that way or something or like
how do you know when you want to admit a
certain term or Etc yeah great way to
put it so this is like equation
2.6 um where we have the expected free
energy
here usually people talk about this
first decomposition between the
epistemic value expected Information
Gain and the pragmatic value the
preference or the constraint satisfies
but again these are equivalent um or
bounded derivations now in this figure
here's pragmatic value here is epistemic
value so just just
briefly um and and these equations also
again another area where where people
can look is using the ontology
here's natural language ways to read
these equations because the letters
don't matter it's about the ontological
relationships so this is free energy
expected free energy on Pi the policy
prior
distribution is an
expectation about the variational
distribution about the expected sequence
of observations y Tilda conditioned upon
which action we're going to choose
about How likely those observations are
in light of our preferences that's
pragmatic value How likely is the
observations how are those observations
going to be linked with our prior
preferences on observations and then
epistemic value component the double
line is like the KL Divergence
separator looking at these two sides
they're pretty similar like they both
have have QX Tilda conditioned on Pi so
that's my variational distribution of
what latent States I expect to unfold
conditioned upon the action that I
choose the difference is here we have
what are going what is my variational
Distribution on the observations that I
expect to see conditioned upon the
latent
States here is the observations I expect
to see also conditioned upon the
action those are what those mean so this
is saying if the
action is not expected to change
anything about the
observations received then the epistemic
value of the action is going to be low
whereas if conditioning upon the action
leads to a large difference then it's
going to be high okay now you brought it
up in the context of like wanting a
certain regime of action specializing to
get by dropping out one of these terms
you get certain subtypes that's kind of
the break the puzzle down the build the
puzzle up is you will find many
thousands of Articles discussing these
topics here's a way that we can see that
those are special cases of a more
generic optimization Target function
so if we only have pragmatic value we
get expected utility Theory basian
decision Theory but what would be the
issue with that well we wouldn't be able
to have learning what is the
reinforcement learning approach to that
they try to bring learning into the
reward
function what if you drop pragmatic
value then all observations
are equally
preferable so behavior is driven by just
surprise and learning and that's like
novelty
search or pure intrinsic
motivation so this is sort of revealing
and clarifying that expected free energy
is an
integrated decision-making imperative
that contains some blend of a pragmatic
value and some blend of an epistemic
value
so whether we choose now to zero out
some of those sections to get certain
Behavior or we just want a new lens to
look back on the last Decades of signal
processing and control theory this is
just a helpful way to see that okay how
to inter how to interpret 1 three four
five
yeah K
Divergence between What observations I
expect to see conditioned upon the
policy and the true distribution of the
observations conditioned on my
preferences so this is like KL optimal
control and that this you
know is used as an objective function in
some control theoretic setting
it's yeah yeah and there's other there's
other imperative functions that can be
drawn for example like um Baron millage
and others have clarified like well
there's expected free energy and then
there's free energy of the expected
future but so you know there's some
other imperatives that you could draw up
it's not like this is the only way to do
policy updating and active
inference what what do you mean with
that exactly in the sense that the the
variation of fre energy is the way to go
but in exp energy there's discussion
about what the right way
is I'll I'll like link this in in the
chat this is from
2020 here's another future oriented
imperative function that still is a free
energy so still can be used for V
variational gradient
descent and this is just another another
family of
imperatives to use for policy
updating and this only the case with
expected free energy and the other
variation fore energy there is uh the
consensus of this is the thing to do
um
yes there are different ways to
approximate variational free
energy like this is with um nor AED and
it's it's like okay it's a slightly
different
approximator so there's there there's
some there are some flavors and
choices it's not that there's some
finished singular answer especially when
you start getting into love of data
sets there are some implementations that
may work you know for discreet or
continuous or different kinds of
different other um features of the
specific issue but again this is like
why low road and high road is so
important because the high road and the
analytical directions there they're
system
agnostic their data set independent
they're not talking about computer
languages it's not the operational order
about what comes before this and how
does this variable relate to that per se
on the low road that is the whole
discussion and then the generative model
is the artifact that is entirely
constructed to be viable under those
analytical top- down
descriptions what is the total
discussion in the low road that
contrasts with the high road the the
kind of spe specific implementation
or it's it's um I mean contrast or
complement again that's what chapters 2
and three are about and then we meet
back up in chapter
4 with a train station that can be
reached from both roads because in a low
road we're talking about building these
unified basian cognitive models that
deal with the inbound perceptual and the
out bound action selection period that
has much to do with cybernetics endtoend
variational Auto encoders and so
on top down we're not thinking about one
specific computer implementation let
alone like a data set or a computer
language we're thinking about the
analytical
descriptions of things in their
persistence and
change and then the active inference
generative
model is something like a variational
autoencoder asterisk something like that
but it could be that that is compliant
and describable through that higho
channel but the models that we're going
to look at in chapter 7even and 8 in
discret in continuous time those are the
kinds of generative models described in
chapter 4 which are reached out from
chapters 2 and
three just so for me to understand also
the hyro delivers one true value of the
variation for energy that is delivers
one but it is like open and then there
are different ways to approximated uh
but the Hy does leave out space for what
the exact expect free energy formulation
should
be I'm sure people have different
responses to that I would say there
isn't a singular true variational free
energy for a
system because that's a feature of a
model so the variational free energy is
like an observer approximating a
variable so if we were talking about
well does does the temperature in the
room have a
real L2 Norm a real sum of squares no
different observers could make different
linear models
and they would yield different sums of
squares different R squares different P
values Etc you know is there a true
Anova F statistic for the effect of this
on that or are there just statistic who
are making different Anova and Reporting
their
results so that's the instrumentalist
angle which is people can calculate the
vfv for a
model but the map is not the ter
territory so there might be a vfe for a
map but a map isn't the territory so
that vfe doesn't describe the territory
because somebody else could have chosen
a different variational
family and then they would have gotten a
different
vfe basically everybody has their own
Q right everybody is their own Q that's
what Q is I mean q is like the
individual making you know a model of
the world that's that's where the Q
comes from that's the
approximation it's it's me as an agent
trying to understand and I I have this
generative model that I make of the
process
right is that the
idea exactly and so everywhere you see a
q or everywhere it's talking about a map
this is like a sort of that's why um
Toby St Clair SMI in his dissertation in
in live stream 54 on the category Theory
accounting for the active inference
generative models
he calls it the compositional cognitive
cartography so this is like the science
of the map
making because it sets up the accounting
structure for making
Maps but then how coar grain should the
map be what's the scope what's the angle
what's the ortho project I mean there's
so many questions even if we were just
making a map of
neuroimaging which again returns to SPM
the statistical parametric mapping
making maps of activation in brain
regions or of inferred neural activation
patterns from
neuroimaging and then going from that
map of activation to the posterior
probability Maps so statistical
transformations of those
Maps but by the time you get to
realizing that you're dealing with the
probability
transforms of neuroimaging data
including all the steps of like
registration and
processing any statistic you get out the
other side it's pretty easy to see that
that's a feature of the modeling
process though it has a causal
relationship with the
brain but it's not like there's just one
P
value nor is there one posterior nor is
there one VF for a given experiment and
that experiment was just one of many
that could have been
done okay not sure I'm going to copy
some of these
great comments in
here let's go to
the like
again there's like so many fun things
hidden in here and and what isn't there
is for us to add and
enjoy
okay nice um I have to run it's it's a
thank you last time uh this was great um
I hope to join the next ones thanks for
the all the links and the Koda I'll
check those out y thank you okay all
everyone okay yes thank
you okay
so nacho
wrote I always wondered if there is an
estimation of the actual number of
levels layers present in different
species I believe the number of layers
determine the inference abilities of the
animal is that
right yeah in fact this is an
interesting thing that
um Carl friston will often say oh well
like we make layers with six we make
models with six layers because there's
six layers in the cortex but I've always
been a bit perplexed by that
answer because each cortical layer
though it has six histologically
distinct
strata is actually one unit of nesting
from a
cognitive basian
perspective so how would you determine
the number of
layers
well there might be a situation where
um you can tease that out
experimentally but how does it relate to
structure learning
learning you could have inference on how
many layers should I make this model and
that's kind of where things are at in
terms of like neuros symbolic
programming and procedural generation of
active inference generative models
is exploring model classes that include
different layers and types of
nesting then Ben added gray points
and and there's several papers that have
this sort of two-stroke engine which
also corresponds a little bit to
expectation maximization em
optimization on
structure okay any last um
comments you're muted
Charles I said Ray kerswell has a nice
book called creating Minds which speaks
to the six layers in the cortex as well
I think so he's in agreement with
Carl yeah the six layers are
um are simply anatomical
even though there's like Su layers and
and blah blah blah
but the each each cortical
stack is act here's the six layers right
here each cortical column is one layer
of a basian hierarchical model so even
if there was only two anatomical layers
or 35 anatomical layers per column you
could have a linear conc nation of 75
columns so people focus on the six
because it's clear that there's
something repetitive and important
happening with the cortical
layers that can be seen histologically
from like an evolutionary perspective
and all these other things but there's
no limit to their concatenation
laterally and how many nested layers
that could
have but if you look at this from like a
gener a generalized cord perspective
like you have the position then the
velocity then the acceleration you keep
on going up the derivatives you could
look at real time series and find out
how much variance is in these higher
moments and after you get through a few
moments there's not much to explain for
most time
series would you say that another
way
yeah if you want to
explain or track the movement of a
particle like a car in traffic or
bitcoin price or your blood sugar just
there's some particle that's following
some sort of like really yeah I got
it the first moments of the statistical
distribution is its position right then
there's its velocity like just the
vector of its direction then the
acceleration how is that velocity
changing these are like
derivatives called generalized
coordinates for Real Time series you can
ask what fraction of the variance is
being explained as I add more
generalized
coordinates and this is an empirical
question so it's you could construct one
that has a lot of explanatory value at
the 12th
derivative but just
empirically the explanatory value starts
to get eaten up really fast and higher
derivatives are overwhelmed by noise and
they're
slow so over shorter time
scales the lower
derivatives which is to say nested
models that would have a few layers
explain lots of the variance yeah I got
how many layers and how much of the
variance you need to explain over what
time scale is 100% empirical when when
you're when you're looking at the cortex
horizontally rather than the six layers
vertically how does recursion operate
there I'm not a biologist but I'm just
curious about how the how recursion
operates that's a good question yeah
there's a lot of ways you could get
re-entry as
recursion or reflection and reflexivity
as
recursion
nacho yeah I was uh when I was asking
the question I was also thinking not
just from a neurological perspective but
also from the perspective of psychology
of perception for example if
you if you have to if you're perceiving
something and you say uh in any of the
examples you said before as in a person
that is deciding to smoke and
everything's mixed up in in different
layers different levels first you have
to know that what you have in front of
you is a cigarette so that means that
you have
built uh from the input the sensory
input you've built like a a concept of
what it is a cigarette which is made of
different lines and points and that goes
from the routina the to the tmus and
then to the cortical layers then goes to
to to the cortex so what I was uh asking
is is if there is an estimate of the
number of layers you need because in
each layer you make a different
abstraction you start by row data row uh
points and lines and then those lines
are connected and then you can see uh
how a table or a bottle or a cigarette
is made from these lines and I guess
this is like a new layer from row data
to a concept and then as you go further
up in the in this ladder you get more
abstract Concepts you know what I mean
I'm not sure if I'm oh yes like this is
well studied with Frist and others and
this is flowing through brain regions
with a visual
cortices so there's like Pro but there's
yeah like the visual processing chain
just to get from photons hitting the
retina to just the acknowledgment of
this is a given object a lot goes on
there but cognitive modeling with the a
matrix you might just say all right we
have we have a noisess or a noisy Matrix
that just identifies it and that's kind
of course graining over all of those
like Edge detection and shape detection
steps but if you were studying the
Neuroscience of vision you might delve
more into looking at these Visual
cortices and the what and the where
stream all these yeah I I teach these at
University I'm a professor of these what
I'm trying to do is to connect what we
know from this perspective the classical
studies of visual perception to to the
inference model you know to to the
number of layers you need in the model
to explain this this kind of
stuff
yeah
awesome I look forward to continuing to
unpack that and chapter five okay okay
is probably going to be a great one for
you because it's going to focus on these
three human neural
systems and that'll kind of give a
little bit of a Playbook with many many
references to
[Music]
papers but doesn't look at the visual
but there's a lot of other good visual
papers cool okay can I ask you one last
question okay go for it is top of mine
I'm gonna bring it back to movies you
know that's that's my focus is figuring
out how movies work and uh there's
there's a phenomenon in the movies you
know because surprise is a big part of
making a movie engage you you know but
even if you're watching a bad movie
there's a thing called closure where
you'll you know you're watching a bad
movie and yet you'll sit around to the
end just to see how it turns out because
it's like the mo the brain is building a
model of the world that's going on in
the movie The Cinematic Universe that
you're experiencing and it kind of wants
to know the final answer before it
leaves unless it's super boring and so
on is is there something in the model
that would that would address that Psych
iCal phenomenon of the need for
closure I'm going to give a similar
answer which is really learn the
textbook learn the grammar and then you
will construct many different hypotheses
about how that could be like there could
be a person who prefers I'm the kind of
person who finishes movies or my culture
expects me to finish movies right so
then independent of whether that's their
favorite color on the screen or the
narrative is unfolding according to
their
preferences they still would fulfill
this other preference but then that
would be where you design these
different kinds of differentiating
hypotheses with optimal experimental
design to to get at that but there's a
variety of ways that that independent of
someone's visual hypothesis they could
have narrative preference independent of
narrative or genre there could be just
behavioral
expectations there's so many reasons
because now we're talking about not just
that even the narrative processing we're
talking about someone's interplay
between their own bodily
Logistics and what they want to do with
their own attention in their
day and their uncertainties it's just
like yeah I don't care if if um if John
and Sally end up together at the end of
this
movie but I'm gonna watch it anyway but
you know
that's like well I'm just wondering if
it is it a preference thing or is it a
need for the is it a testing the model
in terms of I built a model of how this
movie is working I just want to see if
the model
Works don't don't close off one road
with it is it a or b just say if it were
a then the generative model could look
like this if it were B the generative
model could look like this now you'll
have two okay how would I differentiate
between if it were a and if it were
B what else could you just keep on
unfolding and that's what the structured
inquiry starts to look like not going
from a qualitative and just saying well
is it this or that well that doesn't
sound viable then just go with this
one but you sketch them
out and then you kind of build up your
space of models that you're
considering even Loosely but you can do
this computationally depending on what
you have available M and then well if
were a what would that what would we
expect to see in this data set versus B
but if a and b give you the
same result on the data set you're not
going to be able to distinguish them so
what data set would you
need that's a good answer thank yeah
it's it's not just about a Vibe check up
front okay thank you okay thank you all
till next time